[
  {
    "i": 1,
    "problem": "1.\\ 120\\cdot(5\\cdot y-6513:13)=43200:90.&\n",
    "solution": "1. $120\\cdot(5\\cdot y-6513:13)=43200:90,\\ 120\\cdot(5\\cdot y-501)=480,\\ 5\\cdot y-501=480:120=4,\\ 5\\cdot y=501+4=505,\\ y=505:5=101.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 2,
    "problem": "2.\\ 7\\cdot(4216-x)=9149.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "2. $7\\cdot(4216-x)=9149,\\ 4216-x=9149:7=1307,\\ x=4216-1307=2909.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 3,
    "problem": "3.\\ (x-8365):6=2108.&\n",
    "solution": "3. $(x-8365):6=2108, x-8365=2108\\cdot6=12648,\\ x=12648+8365=21013.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 4,
    "problem": "4.\\ 770:(4\\cdot x+18\\cdot x)-12=23.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "4. $770:(4\\cdot x+18\\cdot x)-12=23,\\ 770:(22\\cdot x)-12=23,\\ 770:(22\\cdot x)=23+12=35,\\ 22\\cdot x=770:35=22,\\ x=22:22=1.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 5,
    "problem": "5.\\ (180:a+15\\cdot3):8=54:9.&\n",
    "solution": "5. $(180:a+15\\cdot3):8=54:9,\\ (180:a+45):8=6,\\ 180:a+45=6\\cdot8=48,\\ 180:a=48-45=3,\\ a=180:3=60.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 6,
    "problem": "6.\\ 423:(64-x)=47.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "6. $423:(64-x)=47,\\ 64-x=423:47=9,\\ x=64-9=55.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 7,
    "problem": "7.\\ (25-312:y)\\cdot5+25=83+27.&\n",
    "solution": "7. $(25-312:y)\\cdot5+25=83+27,\\ (25-312:y)\\cdot5+25=110,\\ (25-312:y)\\cdot5=110-25=85,\\ 25-312:y=85:5=17,\\ 312:y=25-17=8,\\ y=312:8=39.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 8,
    "problem": "8.\\ 245+(188-29\\cdot x):6=17990:70.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "8. $245+(188-29\\cdot x):6=17990:70,\\ 245+(188-29\\cdot x):6=257,\\ (188-29\\cdot x):6=257-245=12,\\ 188-29\\cdot x=6\\cdot12=72,\\ 29\\cdot x=188-72=116,\\ x=116:29=4.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 9,
    "problem": "9.\\ ((2009+x):3-975)\\cdot25-386=239.&\n",
    "solution": "9. $((2009+x):3-975)\\cdot25-386=239,\\ ((2009+x):3-975)\\cdot25=239+386=625,\\ (2009+x):3-975=625:25=25,\\ (2009+x):3=25+975=1000,\\ 2009+x=3\\cdot1000=3000,\\ x=3000-2009=991.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 10,
    "problem": "10.\\ ((239+x):3-438)\\cdot25-116=2009.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "10. $((239+x):3-438)\\cdot25-116=2009,\\ ((239+x):3-438)\\cdot25=2009+116=2125,\\ (239+x):3-438=2125:25=85,\\ (239+x):3=438+85=523,\\ 239+x=523\\cdot3=1569,\\ x=1569-239=1330.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 11,
    "problem": "11.\\ ((2010-x):3+31):25+211=239.&\n",
    "solution": "11. $((2010-x):3+31):25+211=239,\\ ((2010-x):3+31):25=239-211=28,\\ (2010-x):3+31=28\\cdot25=700,\\ (2010-x):3=700-31=669,\\ 2010-x=669\\cdot3=2007,\\ x=2010-2007=3.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 12,
    "problem": "12.\\ ((2010+x):3-22):25+213=239.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "12. $((2010+x):3-22):25+213=239,\\ ((2010+x):3-22):25=239-213=26,\\ (2010+x):3-22=26\\cdot25=650,\\ (2010+x):3=650+22=672,\\ 2010+x=672\\cdot3=2016,\\ x=2016-2010=6.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 13,
    "problem": "13.\\ (20\\cdot x+36)-5=2011.&\n",
    "solution": "13. $(20\\cdot x+36)-5=2011,\\ 20\\cdot x+36=2011+5=2016,\\ 20\\cdot x=2016-36=1980,\\ x=1980:20=99.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 14,
    "problem": "14.\\ (40\\cdot y-13)+52=239.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "14. $(40\\cdot y-13)+52=239,\\ 40\\cdot y-13=239-52=187,\\ 40\\cdot y=187+13=200,\\ y=200:40=5.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 15,
    "problem": "15.\\ (9\\cdot x-18):7+14=23.&\n",
    "solution": "15. $(9\\cdot x-18):7+14=23,\\ (9\\cdot x-18):7=23-14=9,\\ 9\\cdot x-18=9\\cdot7=63,\\ 9\\cdot x=63+18=81,\\ x=81:9=9.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 16,
    "problem": "16.\\ 20:(33-4\\cdot x)+47=51.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "16. $20:(33-4\\cdot x)+47=51,\\ 20:(33-4\\cdot x)=51-47=4,\\ 33-4\\cdot x=20:4=5,\\ 4\\cdot x=33-5=28, x=28:4=7.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 17,
    "problem": "17.\\ 249-(14+(5\\cdot x-28)\\cdot 3):2=239.&\n",
    "solution": "17. $249-(14+(5\\cdot x-28)\\cdot 3):2=239,\\ (14+(5\\cdot x-28)\\cdot 3):2=249-239=10,\\ 14+(5\\cdot x-28)\\cdot 3=10\\cdot2=20,\\ (5\\cdot x-28)\\cdot 3=20-14=6,\\\n5\\cdot x-28=6:3=2,\\ 5\\cdot x=2+28=30,\\ x=30:5=6.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 18,
    "problem": "18.\\ 229+(14-(5\\cdot x+7):3)\\cdot2=239.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "18. $229+(14-(5\\cdot x+7):3)\\cdot2=239,\\ (14-(5\\cdot x+7):3)\\cdot2=239-229=10,\\ 14-(5\\cdot x+7):3=10:2=5,\\ (5\\cdot x+7):3=14-5=9,\\ 5\\cdot x+7=9\\cdot3=27,\\\n5\\cdot x=27-7=20,\\ x=20:5=4.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 19,
    "problem": "19.\\ ((2014+x):40-8)\\times43-1653=239.&\n",
    "solution": "19. $((2014+x):40-8)\\times43-1653=239,\\ ((2014+x):40-8)\\times43=239+1653=1892,\\ (2014+x):40-8=1892:43=44,\\ (2014+x):40=44+8=52,\\ 2014+x=52\\cdot 40=2080,\\\nx=2080-2014=66.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 20,
    "problem": "20.\\ ((2014-x):80+7)\\times57+623=2390.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "20. $((2014-x):80+7)\\times57+623=2390,\\ ((2014-x):80+7)\\times57=2390-623=1767,\\ (2014-x):80+7=1767:57=31,\\ (2014-x):80=31-7=24,\\ 2014-x=24\\cdot80=1920, x=2014-1920=94.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 21,
    "problem": "21.\\ 898+(2015-2576:x)\\times 13=25000.&\n",
    "solution": "21. $898+(2015-2576:x)\\times 13=25000,\\ (2015-2576:x)\\times 13=25000-898=24102,\\ 2015-2576:x=24102:13=1854,\\ 2576:x=2015-1854=161,\\ x=2576:161=16.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 22,
    "problem": "22.\\ 296+(2015-3222:x)\\times 14=26000.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "22. $296+(2015-3222:x)\\times 14=26000,\\ (2015-3222:x)\\times 14=26000-296=25704,\\ 2015-3222:x=25704:14=1836,\\ 3222:x=2015-1836-179,\\ x=3222:179=18.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 23,
    "problem": "23.\\ 23000+12\\times (2016-1963:x)=45380.&\n",
    "solution": "23. $23000+12\\times (2016-1963:x)=45380,\\ 12\\times (2016-1963:x)=45380-23000=22380,\\ 2016-1963:x=22380:12=1865,\\ 1963:x=2016-1865=151,\\ x=1963:151=13.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 24,
    "problem": "24.\\ 24000+13\\times(2016-1968:x)=48076.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "24. $24000+13\\times(2016-1968:x)=48076,\\ 13\\times(2016-1968:x)=48076-24000=24076,\\ 2016-1968:x=24076:13=1852,\\ 1968:x=2016-1852=164,\\ x=1968:164=12.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 25,
    "problem": "25.\\ 998+17\\times(171-1862:x)=2239.&\n",
    "solution": "25. $998+17\\times(171-1862:x)=2239,\\ 17\\times(171-1862:x)=2239-998=1241,\\ 171-1862:x=1241:17=73,\\ 1862:x=171-73=98,\\ x=1862:98=19.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 26,
    "problem": "26.\\ 947+19\\times(177-1853:x)=2239.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "26. $947+19\\times(177-1853:x)=2239,\\ 19\\times(177-1853:x)=2239-947=1292,\\ 177-1853:x=1292:19=68,\\ 1853:x=177-68=109,\\ x=1853:109=17.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 27,
    "problem": "27.\\ (240239+113\\times x):60-239=3797.&\n",
    "solution": "27. $(240239+113\\times x):60-239=3797,\\ (240239+113\\times x):60=3797+239=4036,\\ 240239+113\\times x=4036\\cdot60=242160,\\ 113\\times x=242160-240239=1921,\\ x=1921:113=17.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 28,
    "problem": "28.\\ (245239+109\\times x):70-239=3294.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "28. $(245239+109\\times x):70-239=3294,\\ (245239+109\\times x):70=3533,\\ 245239+109\\times x=3533\\cdot70=247310,\\ 109\\times x=2071,\\ x=2071:109=19.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 29,
    "problem": "29.\\ 14+5\\cdot a-5=9.&\n",
    "solution": "29. $14+5\\cdot a-5=9,\\ 9+5\\cdot a=9,\\ 5\\cdot a=9-9=0,\\ a=0:5=0.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 30,
    "problem": "30.\\ 11+7\\cdot k-7=4.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "30. $11+7\\cdot k-7=4,\\ 4+7\\cdot k=4,\\ 7\\cdot k =4-4=0,\\ k=0:4=0.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 31,
    "problem": "31.\\ 972-9\\cdot(x\\cdot 5-5+7)=6\\cdot6+7\\cdot9.&\n",
    "solution": "31. $972-9\\cdot(x\\cdot 5-5+7)=6\\cdot6+7\\cdot9,\\ 972-9\\cdot(x\\cdot 5+2)=99,\\ 9\\cdot(x\\cdot 5+2)=972-99=873,\\ x\\cdot 5+2=873:9=97,\\ x\\cdot 5=97-2=95,\\ x=95:5=19.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 32,
    "problem": "32.\\ 808-8\\cdot(x\\cdot5-2+9)=4\\cdot12+8\\cdot8.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "32. $808-8\\cdot(x\\cdot5-2+9)=4\\cdot12+8\\cdot8,\\ 808-8\\cdot(x\\cdot5+7)=112,\\ 8\\cdot(x\\cdot5+7)=808-112=696,\\ x\\cdot5+7=696:8=87,\\ x\\cdot5=87-7=80,\\ x=80:5=16.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 33,
    "problem": "33.\\ 50-(18+4\\cdot x:2):3=10.&\n",
    "solution": "33. $50-(18+4\\cdot x:2):3=10,\\ 50-(18+2\\cdot x):3=10,\\ (18+2\\cdot x):3=50-10=40,\\ 18+2\\cdot x=40\\cdot3=120,\\ 2\\cdot x=120-18=102,\\ x=102:2=51.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 34,
    "problem": "34.\\ 19+2\\cdot x=105.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "34. $19+2\\cdot x=105,\\ 2\\cdot x=105-19=86,\\ x=86:2=43.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 35,
    "problem": "35.\\ 13+2\\cdot x=135.&\n",
    "solution": "35. $13+2\\cdot x=135,\\ 2\\cdot x=135-13=122,\\ x=122:2=61.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 36,
    "problem": "36.\\ 13-220:(5\\cdot x+25)=9.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "36. $13-220:(5\\cdot x+25)=9,\\ 220:(5\\cdot x+25)=13-9=4,\\ 5\\cdot x+25=220:4=55,\\ 5\\cdot x=55-25=30,\\ x=30:5=6.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 37,
    "problem": "37.\\ 11-180:(5\\cdot x+15)=7.&\n",
    "solution": "37. $11-180:(5\\cdot x+15)=7,\\ 180:(5\\cdot x+15)=11-7=4,\\ 5\\cdot x+15=180:4=45,\\ 5\\cdot x =45-15=30,\\ x=30:5=6.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 38,
    "problem": "38.\\ 19\\cdot6\\cdot(15-3\\cdot y+3-y):3=228:3.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "38. $19\\cdot6\\cdot(15-3\\cdot y+3-y):3=228:3,\\ 114\\cdot(18-4\\cdot y)=228,\\ 18-4\\cdot y=228:114=2,\\ 4\\cdot y=18-2=16.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 39,
    "problem": "39.\\ (410-c):7+70=120.&\n",
    "solution": "39. $(410-c):7+70=120,\\ (410-c):7=120-70=50,\\ 410-c=50\\cdot7=350,\\ c=410-350=60.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 40,
    "problem": "40.\\ 3\\cdot(82+(y-5):20)-27=327.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "40. $3\\cdot(82+(y-5):20)-27=327,\\ 3\\cdot(82+(y-5):20)=327+27=354,\\ 82+(y-5):20=354:3=118,\\ (y-5):20=118-82=36,\\ y-5=36\\cdot20=720,\\ y=720+5=725.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 41,
    "problem": "41.\\ 15\\cdot(16+64:x)=300.&\n",
    "solution": "41. $15\\cdot(16+64:x)=300,\\ 16+64:x=300:15=20,\\ 64:x=20-16=4,\\ x=64:4=16.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 42,
    "problem": "42.\\ (x\\cdot14-12):40\\cdot2=12.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "42. $(x\\cdot14-12):40\\cdot2=12,\\ (x\\cdot14-12):40=12:2=6,\\ x\\cdot14-12=40\\cdot6=240,\\ x\\cdot14=240+12=252,\\ x=252:14=18.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 43,
    "problem": "43.\\ 346-x:15-9=14\\cdot23.&\n",
    "solution": "43. $346-x:15-9=14\\cdot23,\\ 337-x:15=322,\\ x:15=337-322=15,\\ x=15\\cdot15=225.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 44,
    "problem": "44.\\ 247-x:14+23=8\\cdot32.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "44. $247-x:14+23=8\\cdot32,\\ 270-x:14=256,\\ x:14=270-256=14,\\ x=14\\cdot14=196.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 45,
    "problem": "45.\\ 156-(y\\cdot40+60):3=16.&\n",
    "solution": "45. $156-(y\\cdot40+60):3=16,\\ (y\\cdot40+60):3=156-16=140,\\ y\\cdot40+60=140\\cdot3=420,\\ y\\cdot40=420-60=360,\\ y=360:40=9.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 46,
    "problem": "46.\\ 1020-(53-x)\\cdot102=204.\\end{array}$\\\\\n$\\begin{array}{ll}\n",
    "solution": "46. $1020-(53-x)\\cdot102=204,\\ (53-x)\\cdot102=1020-204=816,\\ 53-x=816:102=8,\\ x=53-8=45.$\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 47,
    "problem": "47.\\ 54\\cdot(10+28:x)=648.&\n",
    "solution": "47. $54\\cdot(10+28:x)=648,\\ 10+28:x=648:54=12,\\ 28:x=12-10=2,\\ x=28:2=14.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 48,
    "problem": "48.\\ 264:(16\\cdot x-20)=6.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "48. $264:(16\\cdot x-20)=6,\\ 16\\cdot x-20=264:6=44,\\ 16\\cdot x=44+20=64,\\ x=64:16=4.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 49,
    "problem": "49.\\ (x\\cdot12-48):6=18.&\n",
    "solution": "49. $(x\\cdot12-48):6=18,\\ x\\cdot12-48=18\\cdot6=108,\\ x\\cdot12=108+48=156,\\ x=156:12=13.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 50,
    "problem": "50.\\ (170-12\\cdot x):7=14.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "50. $(170-12\\cdot x):7=14,\\ 170-12\\cdot x=14\\cdot7=98,\\ 12\\cdot x=170-98=72,\\ x=72:12=6.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 51,
    "problem": "51.\\ 342-42\\cdot(x-12)=18\\cdot5.&\n",
    "solution": "51. $342-42\\cdot(x-12)=18\\cdot5,\\ 342-42\\cdot(x-12)=90,\\ 42\\cdot(x-12)=342-90=252,\\ x-12=252:42=6,\\ x=12+6=18.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 52,
    "problem": "52.\\ 40\\cdot36-x:53-53=0.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "52. $40\\cdot36-x:53-53=0,\\ 1387-x:53=0,\\ x:53=1387,\\ x=73511.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 53,
    "problem": "53.\\ (9m-75):20-426=27.&\n",
    "solution": "53. $(9m-75):20-426=27,\\ (9m-75):20=426+27=453,\\ 9m-75=453\\cdot20=9060,\\ 9m=9060+75=9135,\\ m=9135:9=1015.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 54,
    "problem": "54.\\ 74-(45-(12-48:x))=35.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "54. $74-(45-(12-48:x))=35,\\ 45-(12-48:x)=74-35=39,\\ 12-48:x=45-39=6,\\ 48:x=12-6=6,\\ x=48:6=8.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 55,
    "problem": "55.\\ 7777:(111-(11\\cdot(66-x)+45))=707.&\n",
    "solution": "55. $7777:(111-(11\\cdot(66-x)+45))=707,\\ 111-(11\\cdot(66-x)+45)=7777:707=11,\\ 11\\cdot(66-x)+45=111-11=100,\\ 11\\cdot(66-x)=100-45=55,\\ 66-x=55:11=5,\\ x=66-5=61.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 56,
    "problem": "56.\\ 6090:x=30.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "56. $6090:x=30, x=6090:30=203.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 57,
    "problem": "57.\\ (38+y)-18=31.&\n",
    "solution": "57. $(38+y)-18=31,\\ 38+y=31+18=49,\\ y=49-38=11.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 58,
    "problem": "58.\\ 210-(14\\cdot x+36):4=180.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "58. $210-(14\\cdot x+36):4=180,\\ (14\\cdot x+36):4=210-180=30,\\ 14\\cdot x+36=30\\cdot4=120,\\ 14\\cdot x=120-36=84,\\ x=84:14=6.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 59,
    "problem": "59.\\ 25-(x\\cdot30+360):70=16.&\n",
    "solution": "59. $25-(x\\cdot30+360):70=16,\\ (x\\cdot30+360):70=25-16=9,\\ x\\cdot30+360=70\\cdot9=630,\\ x\\cdot30=630-360=270,\\ x=270:30=9.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 60,
    "problem": "60.\\ (172-810:x)\\cdot4-90=58.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "60. $(172-810:x)\\cdot4-90=58,\\ (172-810:x)\\cdot4=58+90=148,\\ 172-810:x=148:4=37,\\ 810:x=172-37=135,\\ x=810:135=6.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 61,
    "problem": "61.\\ (1482+144):(242+x)+4=10.&\n",
    "solution": "61. $(1482+144):(242+x)+4=10,\\ 1626:(242+x)+4=10,\\ 1626:(242+x)=10-4=6,\\ 242+x=1626:6=271,\\ x=271-242=29.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 62,
    "problem": "62.\\ \\cfrac{2x}{5,5}=\\cfrac{6}{11}.\n\\end{array}$\\\\\n",
    "solution": "62. $\\cfrac{2x}{5,5}=\\cfrac{6}{11},\\ \\cfrac{4x}{11}=\\cfrac{6}{11}, x=6:4=1,5.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 63,
    "problem": "63. Произведение числа 36 и суммы числа 14 и удвоенного числа $y$ больше 226 на 422.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "63. $36\\cdot(14+2\\cdot y)-226=422,\\ 36\\cdot(14+2\\cdot y)=422+226=648,\\ 14+2\\cdot y=648:36=18,\\ 2\\cdot y=18-14=4,\\ y=4:2=2.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 64,
    "problem": "64. Произведение числа 27 и суммы числа 15 и удвоенного числа $y$ больше 211 на 356.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "64. $27\\cdot(15+2\\cdot y)-211=356,\\ 27\\cdot(15+2\\cdot y)=356+211=567,\\ 15+2\\cdot y=567:27=21,\\ 2\\cdot y=21-15=6,\\ y=6:2=3.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 65,
    "problem": "65. $9\\cdot x -36=99.$ 66. $59+2\\cdot(35-24:x)=121.$ 67. $89+3\\cdot(34-24:x)=182.$\\\\\n$\\begin{array}{ll}\n",
    "solution": "65. $9\\cdot x -36=99,\\ 9\\cdot x=99+36=135,\\ x=135:9=15.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 66,
    "problem": "68.\\ 2021-(x\\times15+13):4=1114.& 69.\\ 2021-(x\\times15+14):4=1125.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "66. $59+2\\cdot(35-24:x)=121,\\ 2\\cdot(35-24:x)=121-59=62,\\ 35-24:x=62:2=31,\\ 24:x=35-31=4,\\ x=24:4=6.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 67,
    "problem": "70.\\ 2022-(61+x\\times31):6=126.& 71.\\ 2022-(59+x\\times29):6=248.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "67. $89+3\\cdot(34-24:x)=182,\\ 3\\cdot(34-24:x)=182-89,\\ 3\\cdot(34-24:x)=93,\\ 34-24:x=93:3=31,\\ 24:x=34-31=3,\\ x=24:3=8.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 68,
    "problem": "72.\\ 14+9\\cdot k=203.& 73.\\ 18+7\\cdot k=235.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "68. $2021-(x\\times15+13):4=1114,\\ (x\\times15+13):4=2021-1114=907,\\ x\\times15+13=907\\cdot4=3628,\\ x\\times15=3628-13=3615,\\ x=3615:15=241.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 69,
    "problem": "74.\\ 5\\cdot24-24:(24-2\\cdot k)=54\\cdot2.&\n",
    "solution": "69. $2021-(x\\times15+14):4=1125,\\ (x\\times15+14):4=2021-1125=896,\\ x\\times15+14=896\\cdot4=3584,\\ x\\times15=3584-14=3570,\\ x=3570:15=238.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 70,
    "problem": "75.\\ 2023 - (23 + x \\times 61) : 11 = 141.\\\\\n",
    "solution": "70. $2022-(61+x\\times31):6=126,\\ (61+x\\times31):6=2022-126=1896,\\ 61+x\\times31=1896\\cdot6=11376,\\ x\\times31=11376-61=11315,\\ x=11315:31=365.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 71,
    "problem": "76.\\ 2023 - (39 + x \\times 91) : 13 = 417,&\n",
    "solution": "71. $2022-(59+x\\times29):6=248,\\ (59+x\\times29):6=2022-248=1774,\\ 59+x\\times29=1774\\cdot6=10644,\\ x\\times29=10644-59=10585,\\ x=10585:29=365.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 72,
    "problem": "77.\\ (64 - 9 \\cdot h) \\cdot 42 = 798,\\\\\n",
    "solution": "72. $14+9\\cdot k=203,\\ 9\\cdot k=203-14=189,\\ k=189:9=21.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 73,
    "problem": "78.\\ (73 - 7 \\cdot p) \\cdot 23 = 874,&\n",
    "solution": "73. $18+7\\cdot k=235,\\ 7\\cdot k=235-18=217,\\ k=217:7=31.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 74,
    "problem": "79.\\ 1273+(50632-239\\times x):13=2024,\\\\\n",
    "solution": "74. $5\\cdot24-24:(24-2\\cdot k)=54\\cdot2,\\ 120-24:(24-2\\cdot k)=108,\\ 24:(24-2\\cdot k)=120-108=12,\\ 24-2\\cdot k=24:12=2,\\ 2\\cdot k=24-2=22,\\ k=22:2=11.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 75,
    "problem": "80.\\ 1305+(50694-239\\times x):13=2024.\n\\end{array}$\n\\newpage\n",
    "solution": "75. $2023 - (23 + x \\times 61) : 11 = 141,\\ (23 + x \\times 61) : 11 =2023-141=1882,\\ 23 + x \\times 61=1882\\cdot11=20702,\\ x \\times 61=20702-23=20679,\\ x=20679:61=339.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 76,
    "problem": null,
    "solution": "76. $2023 - (39 + x \\times 91) : 13 = 417,\\ (39 + x \\times 91) : 13 = 2023-417=1606,\\ 39 + x \\times 91=1606\\cdot13=20878,\\ x \\times 91=20878-39=20839,\\ x=20839:91=229.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 77,
    "problem": null,
    "solution": "77. $(64 - 9 \\cdot h) \\cdot 42 = 798,\\ 64 - 9 \\cdot h=798:42=19,\\ 9 \\cdot h=64-19=45,\\ h=45:9=5.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 78,
    "problem": null,
    "solution": "78. $(73 - 7 \\cdot p) \\cdot 23 = 874,\\ 73 - 7 \\cdot p=874:23=38,\\ 7 \\cdot p=73-38=35,\\ p=35:7=5.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 79,
    "problem": null,
    "solution": "79. $1273+(50632-239\\times x):13=2024,\\ (50632-239\\times x):13=2024-1273=751,\\ 50632-239\\times x=751\\cdot13=9763,\\ 239\\times x=50632-9763=40869,\\ x=40869:239=171.$\\\\\n"
  },
  {
    "i": 80,
    "problem": null,
    "solution": "80. $1305+(50694-239\\times x):13=2024,\\ (50694-239\\times x):13=2024-1305=719,\\ 50694-239\\times x=719\\cdot13=9347,\\ 239\\times x=50694-9347=41347,\\ x=41347:239=173.$\n\\newpage\n"
  }
]